Inventory of the Albert Hubbard Moffitt papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Albert Hubbard Moffitt papers
1940-1983
85029
Moffitt, Albert Hubbard.
7 manuscript boxes (2.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives
Orders, reports, memoranda, proclamations, press releases, statistics, charts, and correspondence, relating to the evacuation of Japanese Americans from the West Coast of the United States during World War II, and to relocation of displaced persons in Europe at the end of the war.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1985.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
A Lieutenant colonel in the United States Army, Moffitt was the executive officer of the Wartime Civil Control Administration from 1941 to 1943.
The Wartime Civil Control Administration, which operated under the Western Defense Command of the United States Army, provided for the evacuation and temporary resettlement of Japanese and Japanese-Americans in areas of the Pacific coast during World War II. The department oversaw all aspects of the evacuation operations, including assembly centers, transportation, and the transfer of evacuees to the jurisdiction of the War Relocation Authority, which was responsible for the relocation, maintenance, and supervision of evacuees and operated the internment camps.
Source: Federal Records of World War II, Vol. II: Military Agencies, Sec. 1096
Scope and Content of Collection
The Albert Hubbard Moffitt papers contains printed material regarding Japanese-American evacuation, relocation, and internment during World War II. The collection contains personal material, publicity materials, and official memos and other materials that were circulated within divisions and organizations. The publicity materials consist of copies of civilian exclusion orders for the entirety of California, as well as other publications and notices regarding relocation orders. The official material, divided among the respective divisions and administrations, contains memos, maps and charts, statistical records of populations relocated, press releases, and reports on the process of the Japanese-American relocation from California, Oregon, and other states in the western United States.
United States. Army.; United States. Wartime Civil Control Administration.; Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Alaska.; World War, 1939-1945--Europe.; World War, 1939-1945--Japanese Americans.; World War, 1939-1945--Refugees.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.
- Personal materials, December 1941-December 1943 (Box-folder 1: 1-4)
- Western Defense Command Official internal orders, 1941-1943 (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Western Defense Command and 4th Army Headquarters regulations, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 1: 6)
- Wartime Civil Control Administration (WCCA) records, 1941-1943
  - Wartime Civil Control Administration (WCCA) Operation Manual, June 1942 (Box-folder 1: 7-8)
  - Wartime Civil Control Administration organization charts, March 1943 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Wartime Civil Control Administration office memoranda and administrative orders, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 1: 10-11)
  - Wartime Civil Control Administration administrative and office memoranda, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 2: 1-3)
  - Wartime Civil Control Administration (WCCA) press releases, 1942-1943
    - March 1, 1942 - March 15, 1942 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - March 24, 1942 - April 29, 1942 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - April 30 - May 22, 1942 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - May 23 - July 29, 1942 (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - August 3 - October 28, 1942 (Box-folder 2: 8)
    - November 2, 1942 - March 15, 1943 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Wartime Civil Control Administration Index of Cities and Towns in Military Areas 1 and 2, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Wartime Civil Control Administration Bulletins regarding Japanese population and employment, March - April, 1940 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Wartime Civil Control Administration assembly centers and relocation projects, 1942 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Wartime Civil Control Administration Daily Recapitulation, Population Changes in Assembly and Relocation Centers, July - November, 1942 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Wartime Civil Control Administration Daily Recapitulation, Population Changes in Assembly and Relocation Centers, 1942 (Box-folder 3: 6)
- Civil Affairs Division records, 1942-1943
  - Publications, memoranda, directories, and reorganization memoranda, March - October, 1943 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Civil Affairs Division and Western Defense Command Fiscal and Procurement Division procedures, June - September, 1943 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Military files, directories and changes, memoranda, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 3: 9-10)
- Japanese Relocation orders and other materials, 1942
  - Plan of Movement of Japanese to Relocation Centers, 1942 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Military Area No. 1: Proposed Japanese Evacuation Operations Vol. 1, Exclusion Orders 1-50, 1942 (Box-folder 4: 2-3)
  - Proposed Japanese Evacuation Operations, Military Area II, Volume II, Exclusion Orders No. 51-99, May 1942 (Box-folder 4: 4-5)
  - Proposed Japanese Evacuation Operations, Military Area II, Volume III, June-July 1942 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Proclamations, executive orders, and miscellaneous data on evacuation, 1942 (Box-folder 4: 7-8)
- Alaska Travel Control records, 1942-1943
  - Data Regarding Alaska Travel Control, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Alaska Travel Control Staff Memorandum Book, 1942 (Box-folder 5: 1-2)
- Correspondence regarding FBI investigations, April 1942 (Box-folder 5: 3)
- Newspaper clippings on the congressional commission on wartime relocation, 1981-1983 (Box-folder 5: 4)
- Western Defense Command and Fourth Army, Statistical Division, Bulletin 12, March 15, 1943 (Box 5)
- Evacuation Operations, Pacific Coast Military Areas, report of the Federal Reserve Bank of San Francisco, 1942 (Box 5)
- Un-American Activities in California, Report of the Joint Fact-Finding Committee to the 55th California Legislature, Sacramento, 1943 (Box 5)
- Civilian orders, 1942-1943
  - Civilian restrictive orders, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Civilian exclusion orders 1-99, March-May, 1942 (Box-folder 6: 2-3)
  - Civilian exclusion orders 1-99, 1942 (Box-folder 6: 4)
- Committee of Center Managers, Report on the Study of Certain Aspects of Japanese Evacuation, November-December 1942 (Box-folder 6: 5)
- "The Japanese Question in the United States: A Compilation of Memoranda" by Lt. Com. K. D. Pringle (Box-folder 6: 6)
- "Records and Data for Captain Moffitt, Train Commander for Japanese Repatriates, Trip to New York,", June 1942 (Box-folder 6: 7)
- Printed materials on displaced persons, European Theater, 1944-1950 (Box-folder 6: 8)
- "Allied Expeditionary Force: Displaced Persons Registration Instructions,", June 1944 (Box-folder 6: 9)
- Repatriation forms and memoranda, 1942 (Box-folder 6: 10)
- Western Defense Command and Fourth Army, Wartime Civil Control Administration: "Proclamations, Exclusion, Restrictive Orders and Collateral Documents,", 1942 (Box 7)
- Final Report: Japanese Evacuation from the West Coast, 1942 (Box 7)